Command line tools for OA4MP

These are a set of programs that are accessible from a CLI (command line interface) allow an administrator to do CRUD (Create, Read, Update and Delete) operations on client records and approvals. There is also the option to copy a store completely from one store to another.

Getting the tools

OAuth 1.0a

The latest version of the Oauth 1.0a command line tool is available at oa4mp-cli.jar You should also get the script that runs this too, oa4mp-cli

NOTE that OAuth 1 is no longer being updated!! It is kept for those services still seeking to smoothly transition to OAuth 2.

Oauth 2.0

The latest version of the Oauth 2.0 command line tool is available at oa2-cli.jar You should also get the script that runs this too, oa2-cli

Configuration

The tool uses a standard configuration file exactly like the server. Indeed, you can just point the tool at the server configuration file. You will need to supply the name of the configuration in the file you want to use. Aliases can be quite handy here. Given the abilities of the CLI to do quick copies of the store, it pays to have a backup (file) store configured and occasionally simple copy the active store to that. There are many possible uses. It is assumed that the tools are installed in a location called $OA4MP_HOME. Normally the default for this is

OAuth 1.0a: OA4MP_HOME=/opt/oa4mp

OAuth 2.0: OA4MP_HOME=opt/oa2 Note that we will be discussing the OA4MP tools rather than the OA2 tools in what follows. Everything here works the same if you replace oa4mp-* by oa2-*

The assumption of the script is that files are in the following directory structure

$OA4MP_HOME/etc/admin-cfg.xml - the configuration file
$OA4MP_HOME/lib/oa4mp-cli.jar - the jar containing the CLI
$OA4MP_HOME/bin/oa4mp-cli - the script for running this. Be sure it is set to be executable.

The default name of the configuration is assumed to be "default" (no quotes). If you invoke the script with no arguments it will use this and the above configuration file.

Running the CLI

Invocation from the command line is usually done with the supplied shell script, oa4mp-cli. The invocation syntax is

oa4mp-cli [configName configFile]

You should run this as root and might need to set the script to be executable if it is not. If you give neither arguments then defaults are used. Invoke with the argument "--help" for more information. If you give one argument it is assumed to be the configuration name in the default configuration file.

Command line options for the jar.

You should run this from the script, but if you want or need to specify invoke the jar directly, the invocation options they are listed here.

Argument | Value required? | Required? | Description
-cfg | Y | Y | The full path to the configuration file.
-name | F | F | The name of the configuration within the file. If there is a single configuration in the file, then no name is needed. If there are multiple configurations you must specify which one to use.
-log | F | F | The full path log file. If this is not specified then a file named "log.xml" is dumped into the invocation directory.
-use | F | F | Specify the component to use. Rather than loading the whole CLI then use-ing a components (such as clients) you may simply specify that here.
-v | F | F | No argument. Turns on verbose logging so that much more information is dumped onto the console. This is useful for debugging or just if you want to see what it is up to.

    java -jar oa4mp-cli.jar -cfg /path/to/cfg.xml -name myConfig -log /path/to/mylog.xml -use approvals

This would load the configuration named "myConfig" from the given file, write the log to a file called "mylog.xml" and bring up the approvals component.

Running the tool

The CLI consists of utilities for each component that can be used. Once invoked you will see the startup banner and prompt:

[mybox bin]# ./oa4mp-cli
**********************************************************
* OA4MP CLI (Command Line Interpreter)                   *
* Version 4.4.1                                          *
* By Jeff Gaynor  NCSA                                   *
*  (National Center for Supercomputing Applications)     *
*                                                        *
* type 'help' for a list of commands                     *
*      'exit' or 'quit' to end this session.             *
**********************************************************
oa2>

If you type "--help" You will get

oa2>--help

Here are the commands available:
use
load
To get more information on a command type

command --help

Basic supported commands are

use - specify a component to use.
load configName [configFile] - load the given named configuration from the current config file. Specify the config file if you need a different one.

To see the help for, say, the use command you would issue

 oa2> use --help

 Choose the component you wish to use.
 you specify the component as use + name. Supported components are
 clients - edit client records
 approvals - edit client approval records
 copy - copy an entire store.

 e.g.

 use clients

 will call up the client management component.
 Type 'exit' when you wish to exit the component and return to the main menu

Each of these components; clients, approvals and copy is described in detail below. But first, a few preliminary notions.

Index vs. Unique ID

Since most objects have unique identifiers, you can specify these are arguments at any time it makes sense to do so by prefixing the id with a forward slash, "/". If there is a list of objects, you can also specify the index on the list as the target of the operation. The ls command will list everything in the active component.

After you issue an ls (no arguments) you will see a complete list of items in the store. These are numbered on the right hand side. This is the item's index. You may then specify the index directly. E.g. to print out a long version of the item with index 4 issue

ls 4

Typically you will know the unique identifier for an item and you can enter this if you escape it with a forward slash (/). To give the long listing of an object with unique identifier myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/client/a4b78549990 you would issue

ls /myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/client/a4b78549990

Note that since there is no canonical ordering of objects in a store, you should always issue an ls before using the index. It is generally always safer to use the unique identifier.

Setting a default id

If you are working on a single item in the store, you may sinple set a default id to be used for all operations with the

    set_id id

command. Related is the get_id to display the current id and the clear_id to clear it. If you have an default id set, you do not need to specify one.

    oa2>set_id foo:bar/34456
    oa2>ls -l
  name : My test thing
    id : foo:bar/34456

In this case, the details (long form) for the listing of the object are displayed. Had you issued

    ls -l /fnord:46456

The long form for this object would be displayed, since the final argument overrides the default.

Options supported in each storage tool.

size - number of entries in the current component.
ls [index | /uniqueId] - list all items or the details of a given item
update [index | /uniqueId] - edit the item
rm [index | /uniqueId] - remove an entry
create [uniqueId] - create a new entry with the optional id.
serialize [-file path] uniqueId - serialize, i.e. store the object in XML format to the file. Omitting the file dumps it to the command line
deserialize [-new] -file path - deserialize i.e. read in the object from a file. The -new flag tells whether the object is new or not. If new and the id is in use, the operation will fail.

Each of these in turn will be discussed in detail.

Common commands for all storage components.

Getting The Number Of Objects In a Component.

This will print the number of elements in the current storage component.
Example. For showing the number of clients in a store you would have something like the following

oa2>use clients
  clients >size
    Current store has 22 entries
  clients >exit
exiting ...
oa2>

Listing Object or Details of an Object.

    ls [-l | -a | -la | -al] [id]

This lists every element in the current component. The default is to sort by the given identifier, except clients which are sorted by creation date. At this point, sorting behavior cannot be changed. Each record is recorded on a single line. No argument prints out everything in the store. Giving the optional index or unique identifier will print a detailed listing of the object. Here are the command line switches that this understands:

>

-l = long form of the listing
-a = list ALL the elements in the store. Default is short form
-la or -al = long form of all objects in the store. This may be immense. It may be useful for getting a text dump.

Example. Listing a specific object by unique identifier

oa4mp >use approvals
  approvals >ls
    0. (?) myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/adminClient/1105e0486abc6cab6d2450893d9394f6/1586446927641 by "junit" on 2020-04-09 10:42:08.0
    1. (?) myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/adminClient/11daaae5d58ec7e5ba6bb88189fc3bb8/1586446926819 by "junit" on 2020-04-09 10:42:07.0
    2. (?) myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/adminClient/131d41a607efa5be7cd611f56d1060c6/1581113647370 by "junit" on 2020-02-07 16:14:07.0
    3. (?) myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/adminClient/1332c1e8775d827e66e77c5c4c47d23f/1581513221096 by "junit" on 2020-02-12 07:13:41.0
  approvals >

By default (no arguments) it prints out the short form of every item in the store. To now print out the details on number 1:

>

    approvals >ls -l 2
    approval_ts : 2020-02-07 16:14:07.0
       approved : true
       approver : junit
      client_id : myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/adminClient/131d41a607efa5be7cd611f56d1060c6/1581113647370
         status : none

We could have done the exact same thing by simply using the unique identifier:

    approvals>ls -l /myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/adminClient/131d41a607efa5be7cd611f56d1060c6/1581113647370

Updating (aka Editing) Objects.

    update [-key k [-value v]] [-keys [k0,k1,...] [id]

This will let you update or edit an existing object or the properties in one. If you supply no argument except an id, you will be sequentially prompted for every property of the object. The general function is shown below. Current object values are shown in [ ]'s and simply hitting return will preserve the current value.
Example. Edit a client record. In this case we want to make this client use limited proxies.

    clients >set_id testScheme:oa4md,2018:/client_id/79d0237f26f56ee831b033b7eec5865d
    clients >ls -l
        callback_uri : ["https:/baz.foo.edu/client2/7Vgs2kO-sF4/ready1","https:/baz.foo.edu/client2/7Vgs2kO-sF4/ready2"]
                 cfg : {"version":"aOfSNXcKu7VU3qPqc_lnvQ"}
           client_id : testScheme:oa4md,2018:/client_id/79d0237f26f56ee831b033b7eec5865d
         creation_ts : 2020-04-10 08:42:33.0
               email : bob@7Vgs2kO-sF4.foo.bar
           error_url : https://baz.foo.edu/home/7Vgs2kO-sF4/error
            home_url : https://baz.foo.edu/7Vgs2kO-sF4/home
    last_modified_ts : 2020-04-10 08:42:33.0
                ldap : [{"ldap":{"id":"","name":"","enabled":false,"failOnError":false,"notifyOnFail":false,"address":"foo.bar.edu","port":-...
                name : Test client 7Vgs2kO-sF4
       proxy_limited : false
       public_client : false
          public_key : t37mvHp25SkDRQqZ1mx74TiC4qIn_TRtgh5PA9P8VcTORzfJD1cKngU9yiXHMjdTNqYbaoa8vfyNWx0LfQ652A
         rt_lifetime : 456767875477
              scopes : ["openid","email","profile","org.cilogon.userinfo"]
         sign_tokens : true
    clients >

Let's change the name:

    update -key name -value "My other test client"

and let's look at the value directly

    clients>ls -key name
    My other test client

You can also update several properties at once by nassing in a list:

    clients>update -keys [sign_tokens,name]

and you will be prompted in turn for each.

Creating a new object

To create a new object, you must supply a unique identifier. This does not need to be escaped with a /. Once created, you will be given the option of editing it. You may enter any valid identifier as long as it is a valid URI
Example. Crreating a new admin client. This will create a new admin client with a specified identifier. If no identifier were supplied a random one would have been created.

    admins>create my:new:client
    Created object with id "my:new:client"

The object already exists in the store by this point. We will be given the option to edit it (equivalent to issuing the update command against its unique id):

      edit [y/n]?y
    Update the values. A return accepts the existing or default value in []'s
      enter the identifier[my:new:client]:

and you will be prompted for several more bits of information. Now the completed, new client is displayed and we are prompted if we want to keep the changes. Rather than drag you through each update, here is the finished client.

    here is the complete client:
          admin_id : foo:bar
       creation_ts : Thu Apr 23 17:19:36 CDT 2020
             email : bob@foo.bar
  last_modified_ts : 2020-04-23 17:19:36.752
       max_clients : 50
              name : My client
            secret : 126a1356375daf2951e4c8660a098f7264579853
    save [y/n]?y
    client updated.

Removing Objects From the Store.

    rm [-key k] [id]

This will remove either the value in a property or the entire client. If you specify a key, only thatproperty will be affected. If you specify the id of an object, you will be prompted to continue.

Removing an object. This will remove the object completely from the store. In the case of clients you do not need to remove the corresponding approval -- it will be done automatically. However, if you remove the approval record then the client is in effect unapproved until you re-approve it. To remove an admin client would look like the next

> Example. Removing an object by id

    admins>rm /myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/adminClient/13be753b6e816c801e212f0f1cff9d81/1587161772297
      Are you sure you want to remove this client(y/n)[n]:y
    Done. object with id = myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/adminClient/13be753b6e816c801e212f0f1cff9d81/1587161772297 has been removed from the store.
      Removing approval record
      Done. Client approval with id = myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/adminClient/13be753b6e816c801e212f0f1cff9d81/1587161772297 has been removed from the store

Note The remove command will happily remove objects by index, but remember that the indices of all other objects change, so best practice is to only remove by identifier.

Finally, to remove a value, if we had th following value

    admins>ls -key vo
    https://myorg.bigstate.edu

we could removed it by issuing

    admins>rm -key vo

Note that unlike for properties there is no prompt.

Storing objects on disk

    serialize [-file path] [id]

A common enough task is to want to do a considerable amount of editing which the direct CLI is not so well suited for, e.g. twiddling extensive lists of callbacks. This is always component specific, so you must use a comnponent for this to be available. You may serialize any object to disk in XML format, edit it with any standard text editor and then simply read it back in with the deserialize command. The basic syntax is

In this case, the index is as per any other component. The file is optional in the sense that if it is omitted, the result will be dumped at the command line. The file will be overwritten, so make sure you have it right.
Example. Serializing a client.

    cli> use clients
      clients> serialize -file /path/to/my/client.xml /client:sdfsdf:erg98540j034/456eythw456
    done!

Firing up a text editor shows the file which starts to look like this:

    <?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
    <!DOCTYPE properties SYSTEM "http://java.sun.com/dtd/properties.dtd">
    <properties>
    <entry key="name">Updated Test client 42</entry>
    <entry key="sign_tokens">true</entry>
    <entry key="creation_ts">2018-06-28T13:06:28.000Z</entry>
    <entry key="public_key">j75OY1FoPf1AzW5v9KDqTkxrslD1VQhQ5wdVfqUu7pO7SRoMtEwRXqBdFFtNfwmX0Z4l4vbiVRYpq9zGtoMKYw</entry>
    <entry key="rt_lifetime">456767875477</entry>
    <entry key="public_client">false</entry>
    <entry key="client_id">testScheme:oa4md,2018:/client_id/756a9e899981a4cf93f97f40a9da345a</entry>
    <entry key="home_url">https://baz.foo.edu/H2w3GevCrOU/home</entry>
    <entry key="cfg">{
      "config": "updated by converter from old LDAP entry",
      "claims": {
        "sourceConfig": [
          {
     ... lots more

Note that the format is very simple. A key is given (you cannot change these) and then the value is given as the contents of the element.

Reading objects from disk

    deserialize [-new] -file path

This will read an object from a file. This argument is required. This is always component specific, so you must use a comnponent for this to be available. You may specify it as being new, which will also tell the system to create a new identifier for it or it will reject the object if an existing identifier exists. NOTE: This will replace the object, not just update a few attributes. This means that if you just want change the value of an attribute, you have to do it manually.

Example Deserializing a file

    clients> deserialize -file /path/to/my/file
    done!

This will take the given file and replace the contents. A not uncommon use is to serialize a file, edit it and issue deserialization commands against it repeatedly as you debug it.

Invoking the components.

Clients

Invoke as

oa2> use clients

Operations allowed in addition to the standard ones are

approve [index | /uniqueID]
create_hash [string | -file path]

The first will prompt you for the information needed to make a new approval for the client with the given id. The second is used to create a hash for a secret that you supply. This is needed for OAuth2/OIDC clients since we store a hash and not the secret. You may either specify a file containing the secret or type in manually at the command line.

Approvals

Invoke as

oa2> use approvals

There are no extra options beyond the standard ones, however, the create command takes the unique id of the client record you are going to approve. Once created, you may enter the approval information directly.

Copy

Invoke as

oa2>use copy

Supported operation is

cp source target [-verify] - copy source to target optionally verifying

This works over the entire store. It has a single command that will allow you to make a copy of one store (the source) that completely replaces another (the target). This is destructive, meaning that the every object in the target is deleted, so no merge takes place. If the -verify option is used then the two stores are compared once the copy has been completed. Note that this can be very time consuming for a large store! However, if there is any question it is at times very useful.

A custom scope handler

If you wish to add support to an OA4MP OIDC server, you may do this by specifying scopes that are supported in the server configuration file. The client must request these. If you do not specify the additional scopes in the server configuration, then requests for these from a client will cause the server will reject the request. This blurb is about implementing your own handler.

Remember that if you specify a custom scope handler, it will always be called and replaces the BasicScopeHandler which is the default. Even if you do not have a custom scope, this will let you completely rewrite all claims.

The lifecycle of the handler is simple. It is created at server startup and is called whenever needed. This may either be a full implementation of the ScopeHandler interface or, more easily, an extension of the BasicScopeHandler class. In both cases you implement or override the process methods. There are two of these:

  public UserInfo process(UserInfo userInfo, ServiceTransaction transaction) throws UnsupportedScopeException;
  public UserInfo process(UserInfo userInfo, HttpServletRequest request, ServiceTransaction transaction) throws UnsupportedScopeException;

This receives a UserInfo object which has been populated by the server with the default claims. The service transaction has all of the information that the system has on the current user. Simply set whatever values you want returned in the UserInfo object and return that. If you choose the method with the servlet request, then you will be passed the current request, which includes the headers and other information.

Note especially that the UserInfo object has many, many convenience mutators. If you have some specific claims you need to return, simply set them using the put methods or if you need something more exotic, get the underlying JSON object with the getMap call and set the key/value pair directly. The response to the client will take the underlying JSON object and serialize it.

Loading your custom handler.

The easiest way to do this is to extends the environment and simply specify the handler. This consists of 4 steps as follows

Either implement the ScopeHandler interface, or extend the BasicScopeHandler

        public class MyScopeHandler extends BasicScopeHandler{

        @Override
           public UserInfo process(UserInfo userInfo, ServiceTransaction transaction) throws UnsupportedScopeException {
            // Set whatever you need in the userInfo object then return it
            return userInfo;
           }
        @Override
            public UserInfo process(UserInfo userInfo, HttpServletRequest request, ServiceTransaction transaction) throws UnsupportedScopeException {
             // Set whatever you need in the userInfo object then return it
             return userInfo;
            }
        }
    

This example is functionally equivalent to the BasicScopeHandler. The ServiceTransaction passed in is, in point of fact, an instance of OA2ServiceTransaction, so you can see what information is available to the method. Note that not every property in the service transaction will be available. This also means that the current user's name is available in the service transaction. For instance, the user might not have gotten a protected assest (i.e. a certificate) before the call to the userinfo endpoint was made. The transaction also has a getScopes() call. This returns the scopes requested by the user for this specific transaction.
Extend OA2ConfigurationLoader and override getScopeHandler, e.g.

        public class MyConfigurationLoader<T extends OA2SE> extends OA2ConfigurationLoader<T>{
            public MyLoader(ConfigurationNode node){
                 super.node();
            }
            public myLoader(ConfigurationNode node, MyLoggingFacade logger) {
                 super(node, logger);
            }

        @Override
            public ScopeHandler getScopeHandler() throws ClassNotFoundException, IllegalAccessException, InstantiationException {
                 scopeHandler = new MyScopeHandler();
                 scopeHandler.setScopes(getScopes()); // this is a complete list of scopes from the configuration file, if needed.
            }
        }
    

Extend the OA42Bootstrapper to point to this, e.g.:

        public class MyBootstrapper extends OA2Bootstrapper{
        @Override
          public ConfigurationLoader getConfigurationLoader(ConfigurationNode node) throws MyConfigurationException {
              return new MyLoader(node);
          }
        }
    

In your web.xml file, Point Tomcat at your bootstrapper:

        <listener>
           <listener-class>path.to.MyBootstrapper</listener-class>
        </listener>
    

When the server boots, it should find everything and your handler should be used.

Dynamic Client Registration

The dynamic client registration specification is supported in OA4MP as of version 4.2. This means that a trusted administrative client can dynamically create regular clients for use with an OA4MP system. If you have not done so already, you should read the section on administrative clients .

Note: When we refer to a client we mean an OAuth 2 client and otherwise any other will be qualified such as "admin client".

How's it work?

If you are not an administrator and just need a client, you should go to ../oauth2/register. Your request will then be seen by the site adminstrator(s) and once approved, you will be notified. The facilities described in this document allow for a trusted (after vetting, of course) site manager who must manage several OAuth clients to do so without having to resort to the usual vetting process.

How to become an admin

You must register an administrative client as per here.

Implemented specifications here.

The two specifications that are behind this are RFC 7591 and RFC 7592. The flow is that you register an administrative client. This is initially not approved and any operation you try will fail with a message to that effect. We get an notification and once the admin client is approved, it may be used. All calls then create regular (not admin!) clients for use with OA4MP.

The RFCs specify a REST-ful API for clients, so that

POST creates a new client
GET lists what the server knows about this client
PUT will update the client
DELETE will remove the client and all of its information from the server

The toolkit

Included with the latest release on GitHub are a suite of associated command line scripts in oidc-cm-scripts.tar aka the toolkit which contains a complete but minimal functional toolkit. There are basic scripts for each method as well as several examples for using each.

To dynamically register a client you need to make a call to the supported service endpoint, typically ../oauth2/oidc-cm with the appropriate HTTP method and payload. The specification should not be repeated here but the toolkit has a tutorial and many examples. There is also a very detailed readme.txt in the toolkit.

Notes on Legal Requests

What values can be sent and are accepted?

Valid values

Parameter | Required? | Values | Comments
grant_type | N | Either a JSON array of blank delimited list which may contain
authorization_code (default),
refresh_token
urn:ietf:params:grant_type:token_exchange (for token exchange) | If omitted, the assumption is authorization_code. If the refresh token lifetime (rt_lifetime) is specified, then refresh_token is added to the list of accepted grants.
response_type | N | code (default), id_token. | Response types the client may support. If a requested response_type is not on this list, it should be rejected. Note that the initial request always must have the type "code." The others are used at other points and sent along in those requests, e.g. getting a refresh token requires you send "refresh_token" to the token endpoint.
contacts | N | A list or string | This should contain the valid email for a person to contact in case there is an issue with the client. You should assume that if you are going to be contacted at this address it will only be because of some dire issue. Supplying a generic institutional email is useless. The spec. allows for multiples but we only support a single (at this writing) so only the first will be used if a list is sent.
scope | N | Either a JSON array or blank delimited list of scopes | If you wish to use OIDC, you must at least supply a scope of openid. All supported scopes are
openid
email
profile
org.cilogon.userinfo
edu.uiuc.ncsa.myproxy.getcert
Note that the getcert scope requires you be able to get X509 certs via a MyProxy server, so only specify that if you really need it.
rt_lifetime | N | A integer (in seconds) | (OA4MP specific!!) If you request a grant_type of refresh_token, this specifies the maximum lifetime, in seconds, that it will be valid. Normally this is set for a very long time, as in weeks if not months. If this is omitted or set to 0 (zero) then no refresh tokens will be created.
cfg | N | A JSON object | (OA4MP specific!!)This is a configuration that includes scripting for gettign and processing additional claims. Generally you do not need one of these unless you have a very, very specific requirement. If you send attributes that do not fall within the spec., they will be put in this object for you. Generally if you do not know you need it and know what it does, you can safely ignore it.

Extending the Server

The architecture of the OA4MP server (all versions, both based on OAuth 1.0a and OAuth 2.0) is designed to accommodate extensions. The delegation exchanges should, in general, never be altered since there is a high risk of making the system insecure, so hooks have been added in all the places that should let a developer extend the system as safely as possible. There are two main mechanisms involved. These are

Transaction filtering -- intercepting and changing the state of a transaction
Presentation -- changing the look and feel of any user-facing servlet.

These will be discussed in turn. To use this you should check out the most current maven module of oa4mp-webapp and create your own package under src/main/java which will hold any custom classes you need to write. Specifying these in the deployment descriptor should have them compiled and deployed automatically.

Transaction Filtering

Internally, the state of the service is kept in a transaction. This has all the information available to the service on each leg of the delegation. Each servlet implements the TransactionFilter interface, which has two methods:

    public void preprocess(TransactionState t);

    public void postprocess(TransactionState t);

The lifecycle is straightforward: A request is received by the servlet and parsed. The transaction is retrieved from storage and validity checks are made. Once a token is issued, the preprocess method is called. This allows you to intercept the state of the transaction before anything is written to the output stream. Once the output stream is written, postprocess is invoked.

The transactionState contains the original servlet request and response, any parsed parameters (this may be null) and the currently active transaction. To save a transaction, call it t, you must call the store:

getTransactionStore().save(t);

Presentation

Servlets that present something to the user implement the presentation interface. This is extremely similar to the transaction filtering above. The difference being that it is assumed you will be customizing the response for any JSP pages, and an additional handleException method that is invoked on any error that lets you control what is displayed to the user. The entire API then is

    public void prepare(PresentationState p);

    public void present(PresentationState p);

    public void handleException(PresentationState p, Throwable t);

Transaction filtering is still active, so if you just need some special processing and do not need to change the presentation layer, use that.

Table 1: A table the summarizes what each servlet does, and when transaction filtering/presentation is invoked

Servlet name | Purpose | Transaction filtering | Presentation state
RegistrationServlet | Handles registration request for the service. | preprocess:invoked immediately before prepare. Note there is no parameter map or transaction for this, so these are null | prepare:invoked before anything else. First call in the servlet
| | postprocess:invoked immediately before present. There is no parameter map or transaction either. | present:invoked immediately before displaying a page.
InitServlet | Starts the delegation process. Sets initial state and issues a token. | preprocess: invoked after the request for a token has been made internally. | --
| | postprocess: invoked immediately before return, after writing to the output stream. | --
AuthorizationServlet | Authentication with MyProxy. The cert is fetched. The user is redirected to the callback url at the end. | preprocess:invoked after getting the username and password, immediately before fetching the cert | prepare:invoked as soon as the state is determined and the pending transaction has been retrieved. State is set depending upon user action -- see the documentation for state codes if this is of interest.
| | postprocess:invoked immediately before invoking present | present:invoked immediately before page display. This mostly just forwards to the correct JSP page.
AccessTokenServlet | Issues an access token so the client can retrieve a certificate. | preprocess:invoked as soon as the transaction is found to be valid, but before the request is parsed, so the paramter map is null | --
| | postprocess:invoked after the access token has been issued and the transaction state has been updated. This is the last call in the servlet. The stream has been written at this point. | --
CertServlet | Retrieves the certificate that has been previously fetched and returns it to the client. | preprocess:invoked after parsing the servlet request since this is needed to retrieve the transaction, but before the response is written | --
| | postprocess:invoked immediately before returning, after the response stream is written. | --

Example: replacing the cert request.

Sometimes a service need to customize the cert request. Here is a complete example of how to do that in OA4MP OAuth 1.0a. You would want to intercept the request in the AuthorizationServlet, right before the cert is actually retrieved. Simply override the postprocess method:

package my.package;

import edu.uiuc.ncsa.security.util.pkcs.CertUtil;
import edu.uiuc.ncsa.security.util.pkcs.KeyUtil;
import edu.uiuc.ncsa.myproxy.oa4mp.server.OA4MPServiceTransaction;
import edu.uiuc.ncsa.myproxy.oa4mp.server.servlet.AuthorizationServlet;
import java.security.KeyPair;

public void MyAuthServlet extends AuthorizationServlet{
    @Override
    public void preprocess(transactionState state) throws Throwable{
       super.preprocess(state); // required to get certain security headers set in response!
       OA4MPServiceTransaction t = (OA4MPServiceTransaction) state.getTransaction(); // Here is how to use the utilities to create a new cert request
       KeyPair kp = KeyUtil.generateKeyPair();
       t.setCertReq(CertUtil.createCertRequest(kp)); // Note that if you will need the keypair later, you will have to store it at this point.
       // You can use other information, such as the username or lifetime of the cert
       getTransactionStore().save(t);
    }
}

To use this, deploy this in place of the standard AuthorizationServlet in the deployment descriptor (web.xml file).

>Garbage Collection from the command line

What is Garbage Collection?

What is garbage collection?

As OA4MP runs and services requests, transactions and exchange records are created and managed. These are automatically checked periodically for validity and expiration. If they have expired, they will be removed from the system automatically. This is known as garbage collection.

Anatomy of tokens

Every OA4MP identifier contains information about itself. A typical token would be the following:

https://test.cilogon.org/oauth2/429ad35ac99ab5bf8c7383e7499191e4?type=accessToken&ts=1668697283098&version=v2.0&lifetime=900000

This has various parts.

https://test.cilogon.org/oauth2 -- this is the address of the service.
429ad35ac99ab5bf8c7383e7499191e4 -- a unique identifier for this token
type=accessToken -- the type of token
ts=1668697283098 -- the unique timestamp in ms
version=v2.0 -- the version of this token
lifetime=900000 -- the lifetime in ms

Note that in compound tokens, such as any JWT (JSON Web Token) there is always a unique identifier. The identifier will be an OA4MP token.

How to forge a token

You can't. These tokens exist for a prescribed time and must match exactly as strings once created. If the system does not have a record of a given token, it will reject it. In this way, tokens are unique.

How is Garbage Collection done?

Normally you configure it to either work with an interval pause (e.g. Every 4 hours) or can set alarms so that the system will wake up and do garbage collection.

Manual intervention

It is possible to do this manually for various reasons. There are tools to let you manage it.

Assuming you have a functional command line (CLI, see the CLI blurb, you may invoke it from the transactions component. Here are the commands and what they do

gc_check

Check if the current item would get garbage collected.

gc_check [id|index] = check if the transaction would get garbage collected in the current environment.

gc_run

Run the garbage collector or test what would get garbage collected. This will print out a list of ids to the console that were removed. Alternately, it allows you to pipe these to a file.

gc_run [-safe_gc address] [-test] [-file output_file] [-size] - run garbage collection on the transaction store -safe_gc - if present, run in safe mode so that only those transactions in the correct scheme and host will be garbage collected -test - if present, only test which would be garbage collected -size - if present, print number of transactions found -file file - writes the ids to the output file. E.g. gc_run -safe_gc https://cilogon.org would only remove transactions that start with https://cilogon.org The default is to apply garbage collection to every entry in the transaction store

gc_lock

Lock or unlock the stores. If locking is enabled (in the configuration) then stores will be locked during GC. By locked we mean that a special record is written and no GC is allowed to the store until it is removed. Since a lock may remain in certain cases this allows you to set or remove locks. It also allows you to display alarms for locking.

gc_lock [-rm | ? | -alarms] -set [T|TX|all] - lock the transaction and TX stores -rm [T|TX|all] - remove given locks ? - report if stores are locked. -alarms - show configured alarms

Issuers in OA4MP

The open id connect specification requires an issuer, that is to say, the URL of the server that has created or issued the ID token. This is used in server discovery by taking

 issuer + /.well-known/openid-configuration

and examining the returned JSON object to get such things as signing keys, scopes supported and possible claims.

There is a hierarchy for resolving which issuer will be returned with a request, this is

The client explicitly has an issuer set.
The administrative client has an issuer set, but the client does not (so all clients administered have this same issuer unless overridden.)
The server has a globally set issuer in its configuration.
With no issuer set, the default is to use the server address plus the servlet path as found in the HTTP GET request.

Since servers may, for instance, be part of a load balancing system, the actual machine name for the machine is usually a very poor choice for the issuer. Explicitly setting the issuer means that it must be resolvable by a client for server discovery. This is one reason to set the issuer. Another might be for having specific keys used in signing (the server must have access to these and know to use them, of course), however, the issuer must be resolvable as an web address and respond to server discovery.

This has been deprecated in favor of new command line tools. At some point it will be removed.

Manually Approving a Client

There may be times when you need to manage approval for a client. Initially, clients do not have access approved. It may also be the case someday that a client’s security is compromised and you need to disallow all actions with it. This section describes how to manually change the approval of a client. In the initial release of OAuth for MyProxy, there are two methods for approving client request. The first is to use a command line tool that is supplied, the second which only works for mysql-backed stores that directly accesses the database. Administrators are strongly encouraged, if possible, to configure email notifications in all cases.

Using the CLI (command line interface)

The CLI allows an administrator to approve or disapprove a client from a the command line, independent of whether the server is running. The two methods are directly, in which the CLI accesses the store and updates it and indirectly, in which the CLI deposits a request that the server picks up. In the indirect case, the server polls a given directory. This is transparent and is taken from the server's configuration. The CLI works with all stores.

Sample sessions

The easiest way to run the CLI is to check out the module oa4mp-server-api (see the getting started page for how to download it) from svn and build it, then start it from the command line. The build creates two jars, oa4mp-approver.jar, which is the actual program, and oa4mp-server-api-xxx.jar which is the current build. As with all command line java programs, you need to set the class path (Note: This code currently lives in the main trunk of svn. Make sure you have the correct copy. Two samples should suffice. Note that maven will generate its usual informational messages which I am omitting.

Running the jar. There is currently one way to get a jar:

download the source code and run it from within maven

> mvn clean install -P approver

> cd target

> java -jar oa4mp-approver.jar -cfg /home/ncsa/dev/csd/config/oa4mp-server.xml -name in-memory

This points it to the server config file, oa4mp-server.xml and the tells it to invoke the named configuration in that file called in-memory. In this case, the configuration file points to a memory store, there will not be any approvals found. You should see the following scroll past:

logging to file /home/ncsa/dev/main/ncsa-security-all/myproxy/oa4mp-server-api/log.xml

(No entries found. You will need to manually enter the id.)
Enter the number of the client to approve or disapprove, OR, enter an id, starting with a /
/myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/client/77be5883050848c7bb45484cb8567c8e
Enter your approver name:
jeff
Enter Approve or Deny (A/D)
A
Commit changes? (y/n)
y

My responses are in bold-faced. The server must have polling configured or the approval will never be found.

Example against a file store.

> java -cp oa4mp-server-api-1.0.6.jar -jar oa4mp-approver.jar -cfg /home/ncsa/dev/csd/config/oa4mp-server.xml  -name filestore
logging to file /home/ncsa/dev/main/ncsa-security-all/myproxy/oa4mp-server-api/log.xml

0. (D) myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/client/3af1b61bae834e9e373bbd774535ef43
1. (A) myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/client/77be5883050848c7bb45484cb8567c8e
2. (A) myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/client/2ed8e10c4932b284de9fd3d8bdcfc830
3. (A) myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/client/29d1d2b95a29848f77b22b0af129b611
Enter the number of the client to approve or disapprove, OR, enter an id, starting with a /
0
Enter your approver name:
jeff
Enter Approve or Deny (A/D)
A
Commit changes? (y/n)
y

This lists all the approvals in the store and indicates with an A or D if the request has been approved or disapproved. Entering the line number (these are printed on the left) will select the record. You may approve an pending request or disapprove it. Selecting y at the end commits the changes. This also works for any SQL-backed store as well.

Enabling polling on the service.

To allow for client approval polling in the service, you need to set a polling directory and, if desired a polling interval (default is 60000 ms or 1 minute.) What is polling? simply put, for stores where there is no way to directly notify the server of approvals (such as a memory or file store), polling tells the server to check for new approvals at a given interval in a specific location. This does, however, work for any configured storage method including SQL stores, so this mechanism can be used generally. Attributes are set in the server configuration file. For instance, here is a server configuration with polling enabled and email notifications off:

<config>
   <server
        pollingDirectory="/var/www/config/polling"
        pollingInterval="5000"/>
   <-- bunch of other stuff -->
</config>

which stores all transactions, request and approvals in memory and specifies a MyProxy server other than localhost. The server polls the directory every 5 seconds, (which is very often indeed.) You should have the same polling directory specified for the CLI and the server. The CLI puts the approvals there, and the server eventually reads them.

If no polling directory is given, then polling is disabled.

Another method, suitable for testing servers only

This consists of replacing the RegistrationServlet in the web.xml file with the AutoRegistrationServlet. The effect is to automatically approve every client request. This is an inherently insecure system but is of great use when debugging a server deploy. Administrators should feel free to use this but simply revert to the standard servlet when deployment ready.

Direct approval for Maria DB and MySQL stores.

The steps for manually toggling the approval bit in the either Maria DB or MySQL stores are as follows.

Log onto a machine that can access Maria DB or MySQL

Note:Both Maria DB and MySQL allows access per host and localhost access should work but any other should not unless specifically configured to do so.

Log in as the approver (the default username in the install script is oa4mp-approver) to the databasse on the machine where the database resides:

mysql -u oa4mp-approver -p oauth

Note:This sets you to use the oauth database and will prompt your for the approver’s password.

Update the client’s database entry:

UPDATE client_approvals set approved=true where oauth_consumer_key=’myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/client/274ab37ef365b7c384a003bc7’;

Note the single quotes around the id. You should also identify yourself as the approver (usually this is just you email address):

UPDATE client_approvals set approver=’your.name@whatever.org’ where oauth_consumer_key=’myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/client/274ab37ef365b7c384a003bc7’;

In a similar way, you could set the approved flag to false and disallow the client from any future actions. You can check that the update took by issuing

select * from client_approvals;

This will display everything in the database. You could also restrict it to the single entry by issuing

select * from client_approvals where oauth_consumer_key=’myproxy:oa4mp,2012:/client/274ab37ef365b7c384a003bc7’;

Introduction

The authorization module for OA4MP can be replaced by various means, such as using Tomcat's built in management. However, this means that you will need to have separate logins that you manage for each user. Another option is using a proxy service. This is an OIDC service that allows for logins. Your OA4MP can simply forward all requests to that service (including the device flow) and use the service, allowing your users to effectively log in there. In short, it allows some other service to do all your used management.

How does this do it?

You need to register a client with the proxy service (henceforth known as the proxy), then enable using proxies in your server configuration (see below). Since the service is a client of the proxy, you need to enable the callback servlet and register that as the callback.

Configuring the server

The Tomcat deployment descriptor (web.xml)

There is an included web.xml file, called proxy.xml that has a complete setup. Copy that over your web.xml file. The major point is that it enables the callback servlet (with endpoint ready) at

/oauth2/ready

and when you are registering your client with the proxy, you need to set this callback to

https://host:port/oauth2/ready

in a standard install. Key points are that https should be available, and that your server should be at host:port. The proxy must be able to contact your callback endpoint securely, so self-signed certs hould be avoided unless you have a specific agreement with the proxy.

The server configuration proper

You need to have using the proxy enabled within the authorizationServlet tag and set the configuration file as well as the name of the configuration for the client. Remember that this file is the configuration for a complete OAuth 2 client. If you need to, read up on the client configuration file syntax. A very typical entry in the server configuration file would be

    <authorizationServlet useProxy="true"
                          cfgFile="/opt/oa4mp/etc/client.xml"
                          cfgName="cilogon-proxy"
                        />

Using the results

When your service contacts the proxy, a complete exchange is done including getting any claims from the proxy. This means that these are available for your service to harvest. The system will always set the subject to the subject returned by the proxy. You may configure a list of other claims from the proxy to be returned. This is done in the proxy_claims_list property of the client. The options there are

* = (an asterisk) pass along all claims
[claim0,claim1,...] = list of specific claims. Note that putting * in this list will simply return all claims.

So if the proxy returns the following claims

    {"sub":"user_123",
     "idp":"https:shibboleth.big_state.edu",
     "is_member_of":["admin","all-users","admin-phys"]
    }

Then at the least the the server returns the "sub" claim. If you set the client's proxy_claims_list to do so, you may also return the idp or is_member_of claim. If you set the proxy_claims_list to be "*" then all the claims will be passed along.